We are on ערכין Arachin דף ח. Daf Chet. We pick up
from the משנה. Mishnah.
We're going to continue comparing ערכין Arachin and נדרים. Nedarim. ערכין, Arachin,
remember, are the special vows with Torah has its own pricelist for,
and נדרים Nedarim are, you know, just individual vows where you evaluate
the person or object's cost in slave market or regular market. So
the משנה Mishnah says: חומר בערכין מבנדרים. Chomer be'Arachin mibinedarim. So in
the following ways, ערכין Arachin are stricter than נדרים. Nedarim. כיצד? Keitzad?
What's the example? האומר ערכי עלי ומת יתנו היורשין. Ha'omer erchi alai
umet yitnu hayorshin. So if one takes a pledge to give one's
ערך Erach to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and then he dies,
so his heirs still have to pay. דמי עלי, Damai alai, my
value is upon me, which is לשון נדר, lashon neder,
ומת לא יתנו היורשין שאין דמים למתים. umet lo yitnu hayorshin she'ein
damim lemetim. So in that case, the heirs don't have to pay
because you can't evaluate the worth of someone who's dead because dead
people are not sold on the slave market. ערך
ידי וערך רגלי עלי לא אמר כלום. Erach
yadi ve'erach
ragli alai lo amar klum. So if you say, "I want to
pledge the ערך Erach of my hand or my foot," so you
haven't said anything. That doesn't... that is a meaningless statement. ערך ראשי
וערך כבדי עלי נותן ערך כולו.
Erach roshi ve'erach kivedi
alai noten erach kulo. If you say, "I want to pledge the
ערך Erach of my head or of my liver," then you have
to give the full value of your ערך. Erach. זה הכלל, Ze
haklal, excuse me,
so this is the rule: דבר שהנשמה תלויה בו נותן ערך כולו.
Davar shehaneshama teluya bo noten erach kulo.
So the rule for ערכין Arachin is if you try and pledge
the ערך Erach of an individual limb or an individual organ, so
anything which is נשמה תלויה בו, neshama teluya bo, anything which you
couldn't live without—the examples in the משנה Mishnah are your head or
your liver—so then you have to pay the ערך Erach of
the
whole person. If it's something that אין הנשמה תלויה בו, ein haneshama
teluya bo, you know,
like your hand or your foot, where you could live without a
hand or foot, then you don't have to pay anything. That is
a meaningless statement.
However, the משנה Mishnah says: חצי ערכי עלי נותן חצי ערכו. Chatzi
erchi alai noten chatzi ercho. If you say, "I want to pledge
half of my ערך Erach to the בית המקדש," Beis Hamikdash, so
that you can do. Then you would give half of whatever the
Torah's value for that is.
ערך חצי עלי, Erach chatzi alai, if you say, rather than half
of my ערך, Erach, "the ערך Erach of half of me," נותן
ערך כולו. noten erach kulo. Then you have to give your whole
ערך Erach for the same reason as before. That's a דבר שהנשמה
תלויה בו. davar shehaneshama teluya bo. You couldn't exist without half of
your body.
Tell that to my better half.
One could not live without half of one's body and therefore you
would have to give the ערך Erach of the whole person.
So now comparing this again to נדרים: Nedarim: חצי דמי עלי נותן
חצי דמיו, Chatzi damai alai noten chatzi damav, if you say, "I
pledge half of my
value," you give half of your value. דמי חצי עלי, Dmei chatzi
alai, however, if you say, "the value of half of me,"
נותן דמי כולו. noten dmei kulo. In that case as well, in
נדרים Nedarim just as by ערכין, Arachin, you have to give the
value of your whole self. זה הכלל דבר שהנשמה תלויה בו נותן
דמי כולו. Ze haklal davar shehaneshama teluya bo noten dmei kulo.
So this principle that anytime you pledge the value of
one limb or one organ, if it's an organ that you couldn't
live without, you have to give the value of your whole body,
that applies both to ערכין Arachin and נדרים. Nedarim. Of course we
said in the previous משנה Mishnah yesterday that by נדרים Nedarim unlike
by ערכין, Arachin, if you pledge the value of an organ שאין
הנשמה תלויה בו, she'ein haneshama teluya bo, if you pledge the value
of your hand or your foot, you do have to give the
value of your hand or your foot, מה שאין כן ma she'ein
ken by ערכין, Arachin, you don't have to give anything.
So now the משנה Mishnah moves on to another case: האומר ערכו
של פלוני עלי, Ha'omer ercho shel ploni alai, one who pledges the
ערך Erach of another person, not of themselves. מת הנודר והנידר יתנו
היורשין, Met hanoder vehanidar yitnu hayorshin, if both the pledger and the
pledgee die,
the heirs still have to pay. דמיו של פלוני, Damav shel ploni,
if you make a נדר neder for the value of someone else,
ומת הנודר יתנו היורשין, umet hanoder yitnu hayorshin, if the pledger dies,
so then the heirs still have to pay. מת הנידר לא יתנו
היורשין שאין דמים למתים. Met hanidar lo yitnu hayorshin she'ein damim lemetim.
However, if the pledgee, the person whose value was pledged, dies, then
the heirs don't have to pay because again we can't evaluate on
the slave market the value of someone who's already dead.
Alright, so the גמרא Gemara
brings down a similar
ברייתא. Baraisa. תנו רבנן חומר בנדרים מבערכין. Tanu rabanan chomer binedarim mibe'arachin.
So in the following ways, different list from what's in the משנה.
Mishnah. But in the following ways נדרים Nedarim are, I'm sorry, it's
the reverse list from what's in the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah
gave us the ways that ערכין Arachin are stricter than נדרים, Nedarim,
the ברייתא Braisa is now going to give us the ways in
which נדרים Nedarim are stricter than ערכין. Arachin.
So שהנדרים חלין על בהמה חיה ועוף, she-ha-Nedarim chalin al behemah chaya
va-of, so you can make a נדר neder to pledge the value
of an animal, of a domestic animal, a wild animal, a bird.
ואין נידונין בהשג יד. Ve-ein nidonim be-heseg yad. Also נדרים Nedarim don't
have
this discount of השג יד heseg yad if you're too poor, which
we discussed a couple of days ago. If you're too poor to
afford the ערך arach listed in the תורה, Torah, so then the
כהן Kohen evaluates how much you can afford to pay and that's
what you have to give for ערכין. Arachin.
That exception doesn't apply to נדרים. Nedarim. נדרים, Nedarim,
no matter what sort of means you have, you have to give
the full value. גמרא Gemara says
מה שאין כן בערך. ma she-ein ken be-arach. So these two rules
about applying to animals and
not having the discount for a poor person applies in נדרים Nedarim
and not to ערכין. Arachin. חומר בערך מן הנדרים. Chomer be-arach min
ha-nedarim. So in the following ways, this is now a similar list
to our משנה. Mishnah. In the following ways ערכין Arachin are stricter
than נדרים. Nedarim. כיצד? Keitzad? What's the case? אמר ערכי עלי ומת
יתנו יורשין. Amar erchi alai va-met, yitnu yorshin. So one who pledges
my ערך arach and then dies, the יורשין yorshin have to pay.
דמי עלי ומת לא יתנו יורשין. Dami alai va-met, lo yitnu yorshin.
One who makes a נדר neder of my value and then dies,
the יורשין yorshin don't have to pay, שאין דמים למתים, she-ein damim
le-metim, because again we cannot evaluate the price of someone who's dead.
אמר
ערכי עלי ומת יתנו יורשין. Amar erchi alai va-met, yitnu yorshin. So
now the גמרא Gemara just requotes that last line in the ברייתא.
Braisa. One who pledges my ערך arach and dies, the יורשין yorshin
have to pay. So the גמרא Gemara asks, שמע מינה מלוה על
פה גובה מן היורשין? shema mina milveh al peh goveh min ha-yorshin?
So do we hear, can
normally, so there are two types of loans you can have in
הלכה. Halacha. You have a loan that is done
orally with witnesses but without a contract. And then you have מלוה
בשטר milveh bi-shtar which is put into a contract. So the גמרא
Gemara is now assuming that that which you owe to the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash for ערך, arach, there's no specific contract. All you
did was state verbally that you want to make the pledge. And
therefore the גמרא Gemara asks, can we derive from here that
someone who loans money orally can collect the loan from the יורשין
yorshin based on the fact that the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash can
collect its loan, its ערך, arach, from the יורשין yorshin if the
person who made the ערך arach dies? And
the גמרא Gemara says no, you can't learn from here. שאני הכא
דמלוה כתובה בתורה היא. Shani hacha de-milveh kesuvah ba-Torah hi. So this
isn't strictly
an oral loan because this is written down. It's not written in
a contract, but it's written in the תורה Torah that you have
to pay this. So then the גמרא Gemara asks, okay,
but I mean I understand why they're focusing on one part, but
he said דמי עלי ומת לא יתנו יורשין. dami alai va-met lo
yitnu yorshin. So why can't you infer from the other way that
מלוה על פה milveh al peh is not?
Right, but that's because of a technicality. שאין דמים למתים. ein damim
le-metim. לא יתנו היורשין lo yitnu ha-yorshin because we have no way
of evaluating how much they would have to give.
Okay, but you mean if there was a way then it would
be?
I mean that would be the implication, yes.
The implication is that seems to be the difference in the משנה.
Mishnah. ערך Arach because it's a fixed price and we know exactly
how much you give, the יורשין yorshin have to pay.
נדרים Nedarim because you need to do an evaluation and the person's
dead and can no longer be evaluated, we can't have the יורשין
yorshin pay.
And the dead body no longer has any actual market value.
No, meaning you can't, we need to know the value of a
living person. He's no longer here to evaluate. The value of a
dead person is irrelevant. Dead people are also אסור בהנאה. assur be-hana'ah.
You can't, you're not allowed to sell a dead person, so
it's...
they didn't have the concept of autopsy, I mean let's say what
did doctors do in those days? They had very...
what did doctors do? They cut up animals. Yeah.
Right, autopsies on humans are a relatively recent concept in the course
of history.
I was wondering if maybe the גמרא Gemara makes, had that as
a concept and that they could possibly have some use of the
body after.
Right, but then
you can see evidence that they are actually talking about animal anatomy
even when they're talking about human anatomy throughout, especially in נדה Niddah
or like רש"י Rashi will step in and say it's always on
a cow, that's why they think
that.
Oh, I see, so they didn't even have a concept of anatomy?
Was there some leniency in terms of medical learning that it wasn't
considered getting something from the body?
There is no evidence to the best of my knowledge of like
I said of
doctors doing human dissections until several hundred years ago in the Jewish
world or in any other part of the world.
Right, so the גמרא Gemara says, so the גמרא Gemara says, okay,
so שמע מינה מלווה הכתוב בתורה ככתוב בשטר דמי. shma mina malveh
hakatuv batorah kkatuv beshtar dami. So if you want to tell me,
okay, יורשין yorshin only have to pay a loan that's in a
contract and not an oral loan and this and you can't prove
so you can't prove the other way from here because this is
a מלווה הכתוב בתורה, malveh hakatuv batorah, it's not a מלווה על
פה, malveh al peh, it's written in the Torah, it's not strictly
oral. So then let's prove from here on the other side that
a loan which is written in the Torah or a monetary obligation
written in the Torah has the status of being written in the
שטר, shtar, which was a מחלוקת machloket in in מסכת בכורות, Masechet
Bechorot, which we did however however long ago. So
so the גמרא Gemara says, okay, let's prove one side of that
מחלוקת machloket from here.
So the גמרא Gemara says no we can't prove that either. הכא
במאי עסקינן hacha bemai askinan כשעמד בדין. keshe'amad bedin. So this is
a case where this is a case where a person not only
verbally pledged the ערך, erech,
but also also appeared in court and the judge evaluated the language
of his ערך erech and said that was a good ערך, erech,
you're obligated to pay. Once the court actually said you're obligated to
pay, then it's ככתוב בשטר דמי, kkatuv beshtar dami, then then it's
like having a contract, but just saying ערכי עלי, erchi alai, just
saying I want to make the pledge, maybe that is is still
like is still like מלווה על פה. malveh al peh. So you
can't prove from here. But the גמרא Gemara is going to question
this answer. דכיוון דדמי עלי dekivan dedami alai שעמד בדין she'amad bedin
אמאי לא יתנו יורשין? amai lo yitnu yorshin?
So if that's the case that you're going to make this distinction
between
between before the court says he has to pay and after the
court has ruled, so then why don't we say that by נדרים
nedarim also, once he has appeared before court and the court has
ruled it was a valid נדר neder he's obligated to pay,
why do the heirs not have to pay in that case? אמאי
לא יתנו יורשין? amai lo yitnu yorshin?
So the גמרא Gemara says דמי עלי מחוסר אומדנא. dami alai mechusar
umdana. So we need we need two things for נדרים. nedarim. By
ערכין, erchin, you appear in court and we say you have to
pay because it you know it was a valid ערך erech the
way you said it, and we know exactly how much you have
to pay because the Torah tells us how much you pay for
an ערך. erech. By נדרים, nedarim, even if you stand even if
you stand in court and the court evaluates what words did you
say in your נדר neder and says that's a good נדר, neder,
you have to pay, well we still have to do the evaluation
of the person
we still have to do the evaluation of the person whose value
you have to pay.
And so the גמרא Gemara says if that hasn't we need to
know the value also. If that hasn't been done if that hasn't
been done before you before you died, then then it doesn't then
it doesn't get the status of...
And if it has, then the יורשין yorshin do have to pay?
That's that is the implication here, yes. If both if both the
evaluation of the pledger's obligation and the evaluation of the
pledgee's value have been done already, then then even by נדרים nedarim
the the יורשין yorshin would have to pay.
Do we don't do we actually really need העמדה בדין ha'amada bedin
for all these cases? In the standard case, I'm going to pay
his ערך erech I say. Do I do I really have to
go to court and then say oh yeah yeah what you said
is okay? You just normally you just say alright I just pay
and that's the end of it.
I mean I guess if you're not disputing anything then then you
don't need to. I mean I guess if you if you know...
Having second thoughts on it?
Yeah, if you're having second thoughts and you're saying well I'm not
sure do I really want to give that, did I did I
take it the right way? So now you now you go to
court, you ask a שאלה, sheila, well is this is this a
proper נדר? neder? And you know if it is then you have
to pay and if it's not, great. Most most scenarios it depends.
Right.
So so right, so דמי עלי מחוסר אומדנא, dami alai mechusar umdana,
we still haven't evaluated the worth of the person. ערכי עלי לא
מחוסר ולא כלום. erchi alai lo mechusar velo klum. There there are
no remaining steps after
העמדה בדין, ha'amada bedin, assuming you need that.
Right.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara we're going to move on to the
next piece in the משנה Mishnah now. ערך ידי וערך רגלי עלי.
erech yadi ve'erech ragli alai. So that was משנה Mishnah said if
you if you pledge the ערך erech of your hand or of
your foot, לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum, that that is a
that's a meaningless statement, as opposed to ערך ראשי וערך כבדי, erech
roshi ve'erech kivedi, your head or your liver, you would have to
pay ערך erech of the whole of the whole person. So the
גמרא Gemara says אמר רב גידל אמר רב amar Rav Gidel amar
Rav ונותן דמיה. venoten dameha. So you
you
if you say ערך ידי וערך רגלי, erech yadi ve'erech ragli, the
ערך erech of my hand and my foot, so you have to
give the value of your hand or your foot. So the גמרא
Gemara says והא לא אמר כלום קתני, veha lo amar klum katani,
but the משנה Mishnah said you don't give anything. The משנה Mishnah
said it's a worth it's a meaningless statement.
So he says oh no it's a מחלוקת תנאים. machloket tanna'im. לא
אמר כלום לרבנן. lo amar klum lerabbanan. According to the רבנן, Rabbanan,
you're right.
The simple reading of the משנה, Mishnah, you don't you don't give
anything. ונותן דמיה לרבי מאיר. venoten dameha leRabbi Meir. However, according to
רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you would have to
you would have to give the value of your hand or your
foot. That is from a מחלוקת machloket earlier in this earlier in
the מסכת. masechet. where Rabbi Meir and the רבנן Rabbanan argued
אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה adam motzi devarov l'vatalah or אין אדם מוציא
דבריו לבטלה. ein adam motzi devarov l'vatalah. So the רבנן Rabbanan hold
yes אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה, adam motzi devarov l'vatalah, sometimes people do
say meaningless statements and therefore we can assume this is a meaningless
statement as well. Rabbi Meir holds אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה, ein
adam motzi devarov l'vatalah, people don't generally say meaningless statements. Therefore, if
a person said ערך ידי erech yadi or ערך רגלי, erech ragli,
the ערך erech of my hand or of my foot, we assume
that since they knew that in the terms of ערכין arachin it's
a meaningless statement, they must have meant it, they must have meant
it to be a נדר neder and therefore you have to give
the value of your hand or your foot.
That's part of people speaking the
everyday language that they have, a person speaks as opposed to a
purely legal terminology.
So they, right, right, throughout, throughout נדרים Nedarim we see that all
the time, trying to figure out not just what are the halachic
definitions of things, but what does the ordinary person mean when they
say it.
So now the גמרא Gemara says, הא אמר חדא זימנא, ha amar
chada zimna, what what are you telling me this here? We already
know there's a מחלוקת machlokes Rabbi Meir and the רבנן Rabbanan on
this topic, what is, which רב גידל Rav Gidel himself was the
one who told us about. So what is רב גידל Rav Gidel
coming to add to us here? So what was רב גידל Rav
Gidel's previous statement? דאמר רב גידל אמר רב, de'amar Rav Gidel amar
Rav,
האומר ערך כלי זה עלי נותן דמיו. ha'omer erech kli zeh alai
noten damav.
So רב גידל Rav Gidel in the name of רב Rav told
us explaining the opinion of Rabbi Meir that one who says the
ערך erech of a כלי, kli, of a vessel or utensil,
should be on me to pay, he has to give the value,
the actual value of that כלי, kli, even though normally there are
no ערכין arachin by כלים, kelim, by vessels, ערכין arachin only applies
to human beings. But again, Rabbi Meir who holds that people don't
make meaningless statements, if you said ערך כלי זה, erech kli zeh,
we assume you meant it, we assume you meant it as a
נדר. neder.
So מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, so what would I have thought?
Why why if I only had this statement from רב גידל Rav
Gidel and not the other statement from רב גידל Rav Gidel would
it not have been sufficient? So I would have thought התם הוא
דאדם יודע שאין ערך לכלי hatam hu d'adam yodea she'ein erech l'kli
וגמר ואמר לשם דמים. ve'gamar ve'amar l'shem damim. So everyone knows there
are no ערכין arachin by כלים, kelim, there are no ערכין arachin
by utensils, and therefore when he said ערך כלי זה, erech kli
zeh, we assume that since he knows the concept of ערכין arachin
doesn't apply to vessels, he must have meant it, he must have
meant it as a נדר, neder, as pledging its value. אבל הכא,
aval hacha, מיטעי קטעי, mit'ei katai,
but I might have thought that here by ערך ידי וערך רגלי,
erech yadi ve'erech ragli, my hand or my foot, he simply made
a mistake. דסבר de'savar כי היכי דאיכא ערך ראשי וערך כבדי, ki
heichi d'ika erech roshi ve'erech kveidi, איכא נמי ערך ידי וערך רגלי.
ika nami erech yadi ve'erech ragli.
He thought just like you can pledge the ערך erech of your
head or your liver,
so too you can pledge the ערך erech of your hand or
your רגלי. ragli. אבל דמים לא קאמר, aval damim lo ka'amar,
but he didn't intend, he didn't intend to
pledge the actual value of his hand or foot. קא משמע לן,
kamashmalan, קא משמע לן kamashmalan we say no, not like that, that
even even here Rabbi Meir would say that ערך ידי וערך רגלי,
erech yadi ve'erech ragli, אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה, ein adam motzi
devarov l'vatalah, people don't make meaningless statements, he must have meant to
pledge the value of your hand or the value of your foot.
And the חכמים Chachamim who hold people do sometimes make meaningless statements
hold ערך ידי וערך רגלי erech yadi ve'erech ragli is meaningless and
you don't have to pay anything.
Okay, so going on to the next piece of the משנה. Mishnah.
ערך ראשי וערך כבדי נותן ערך כולו. erech roshi ve'erech kveidi noten
erech kulo.
So so the משנה Mishnah said if you if you pledge the
ערך erech of your head or of your liver, you have to
give the ערך erech of the whole person. So מאי טעמא, mai
ta'ama, where do we know this from? נפשות קאמר רחמנא. nefashot ka'amar
Rachmana.
The פסוק pasuk about ערכין arachin uses the word נפשות, nefashot, נפש,
nefesh, a person's life, and therefore we get this rule that anything
that your any limb that your life is dependent on, you have
to give you have to give the ערך erech of the whole
person. זה הכלל, zeh haklal, so going on in the משנה, Mishnah,
זה הכלל, zeh haklal, דבר שהנשמה תלויה בו כלו. davar she'hanshama tluyah
bo kulo. So the משנה Mishnah stated the general rule that any
any limb that your life is dependent on, you have to give
the ערך erech of the whole person. So the גמרא Gemara asks,
לאתויי, l'atuyei,
so
לאתויי מאי, l'atuyei mai, so what is this coming to teach us
that wasn't already in the משנה? Mishnah? So remember we have three
examples of the משנה Mishnah in the משנה Mishnah of things that
are דבר שהנשמה תלויה בו, davar she'hanshama tluyah bo, that your life
depends on. One is your head, the second was the second was
your liver, and the third was if you pledge half of your
entire body.
And the גמרא Gemara of course always assumes that anytime we have
a general rule stated, it must be to teach us some case
that wasn't explicitly in the משנה. Mishnah. So the גמרא Gemara says,
what's the case here? To teach us that your leg cut off
above your knee is also something that you couldn't live without. That
was actually a מחלוקת machloket *machloket* in מסכת חולין Chulin *Masechet Chullin*
in אלו טריפות *Elu Trefot* whether that counts as a טריפה *trefah*.
But this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* clearly holds by the position that it
is.
And so it says if you pledge, if you pledge your whole
leg, not just not just up to your knee, then that's also
called a דבר שהנשמה תלויה בו *davar shehaneshamah teluyah bo* and you
would have to give the ערך erech *erech* of the whole person.
Alright, חצי ערכי
עלי alai *chatzi erchi alai* וכולי vechulei.
*vechulei*. So the משנה mishna. *Mishnah* said חצי ערכי עלי alai, נותן
חצי ערכו *chatzi erchi alai noten chatzi ercho*, ערך erech חצי עלי
alai נותן ערך erech כולו *erech chatzi alai noten erech kulo*.
So if you if you pledge half your value, half of your
ערך erech *erech*, you give half of your ערך *erech*. But again
if you pledge the ערך *erech* of half of you, you have
to give the ערך *erech* of all of you because that's a
דבר שהנשמה תלויה בו *davar shehaneshamah teluyah bo*.
So
where were we? Okay, so
תנו רבנן Rabbanan *tanu rabanan*, so we have a ברייתא Baraitah. *braita*.
חצי ערכי עלי alai נותן חצי ערכו *chatzi erchi alai noten chatzi
ercho*. So the first position in the ברייתא Baraitah, *braita* is just
the position of our משנה mishna *Mishnah*. If you pledge half your
value, half your ערך *erech*, you give half of your ערך *erech*.
However, we now have a מחלוקת machloket תנאים *machloket tanaim*. רבי יוסי
ברבי יהודה אומר לוקה loke ונותן ערך שלם *Rabbi Yossi berabbi Yehuda
omer loke venoten erech shalem*. You get מלקות malkot *malkut*, you get
lashes, and you have to pay your whole ערך *erech*. גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* asks, לוקה loke אמאי *loke amai*? Like what do you get
lashes for? You didn't do anything אסור *assur*. So אמר רב פפא
Rav Pappa *amar Rav Pappa*, no, read it as לוקה בערך שלם
*loke be'erech shalem*. לוקה *loke* is not literal lashes, it just means
you get punished. How do you get punished? By having to pay
your whole ערך *erech*. Okay, so nevertheless why are you getting punished?
מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama*? What's the reason? גזירה חצי ערכי אטו ערך
חציו *gezeirah chatzi erchi atu
erech chatzyo*. It probably should be חציי *chatzyi* though because it's not
parallel with חצי ערכי *chatzi erchi*.
Although this whole דף *daf* has been interchanging ו *vavs* and י
*yuds* at the end, which happens a lot in manuscripts that ו
*vavs* and י *yuds* get interchanged, so it's not always clear which
is which. But so it's a גזירה *gezeirah* since since ערך חציי
*erech chatzyi*, since half of my since the ערך *erech* of half
of me I'd have to give the whole thing and people can
easily confuse that with half of my ערך *erech*, we say we
say according to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה *Rabbi Yossi berabbi Yehuda* that
מדרבנן *miderabanan* if you say either of those languages you have to
you have to pay the whole
thing. And ערך חציי
*erech chatzyi* why do you have to pay the whole thing? הוי
דבר שהנשמה תלויה בו *havei davar shehaneshamah teluyah bo*. So I've been
saying that for a while but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it
explicitly now. The reason why you have to pay the whole ערך
*erech* if you say the ערך *erech* of half of me is
because half of your body is something you couldn't live without and
therefore it's a דבר שהנשמה תלויה בו *davar shehaneshamah teluyah
bo*. So now next piece of the משנה mishna *Mishnah*. So חצי
דמי עלי demai alai, נותן חצי דמיו
*chatzi demai alai noten chatzi damav*. So now now back to נדרים
nedarim *nedarim*. If you pledge half of your value, you have to
give half of your value. דמי חציי עלי alai, נותן דמי כולו
*demai chatzyi alai noten demai kulo*. But if you if you if
you pledge the value of half of you, you have to give
the value of all of you.
So now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama*? Meaning
how do we know? We already established this rule that of דבר
שהנשמה תלויה בו *davar shehaneshamah teluyah bo* that if you pledge a
limb that you couldn't live without you have to give the ערך
*erech* of the whole person. So how do we know that this
rule applies in נדרים nedarim *nedarim* as well? So the פסוק pasuk
*pasuk* says נדר neder. בערכך נפשות לה' *neder be'erkecha nefashot l'Hashem*. The
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* says נדר neder בערכך *neder be'erkecha* which is לשון
נדר neder. *lashon neder* and לשון ערך *lashon erech*. It makes a
היקש *hekesh*, it makes this juxtaposition between ערכין erchin *erchin* and נדרים
nedarim *nedarim*. And therefore we can learn out from ערכין erkhin *erchin*
that the rule applies to נדרים nedarim *nedarim* as well.
Okay, so now זה zeh הכלל דבר שהנשמה תלויה בו *zeh haklal
davar shehaneshamah teluyah bo*. So the again just the restatement of the
same rule by נדרים *nedarim* that anything that your life depends on
you have to give the value of the whole thing. So again
the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara* says so what is the general rule coming
to teach us? And says the same thing by נדרים *nedarim* as
it did by ערכין *erchin*. לאתויי מן הארכובה ולמעלה *le'atuyei min ha'arkuvah
ulema'lah*. It is it is coming to teach us that your leg
above your knee is a דבר שהנשמה תלויה בו *davar shehaneshamah teluyah
bo* and you would also have to give the value of your
whole body. And it applies to both ערכין *erchin* and נדרים *nedarim*,
that's what it's saying. Yes, it applies equally to ערכין *erchin* and
נדרים *nedarim*. Okay, now we have another ברייתא Baraitah *braita* which is
going to actually move back to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*
and חכמים *Chachamim*. So תנו רבנן Rabbanan? המעריך חצי ערך כלי kli.
*tanu rabanan hama'arich chatzi erech kli*. So one who takes an ערך
*erech* of half the value of a כלי kli, *kli* or half
the ערך *erech* of a כלי kli, *kli*. And again normally we
said that there is no ערכין *erchin* on a כלי kli. *kli*,
although we had the מחלוקת *machloket* we already saw before about do
people
make meaningless statements and it's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* who
thinks they
don't assumes that if you say the ערך *erech* of a כלי
kli. *kli*, the ערך *erech* of a... So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
אומר נותן דמיו, that's what we would expect. You give half the
value of the כלי. kli, We assume it's like a נדר. neder
וחכמים אומרים לא אמר כלום, v'Chachamim omrim lo amar klum, it's a
meaningless statement. So let's say according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir I
said I give the value of the sky, what would you do
then? The value of a sky? Do you think this is like
a meaningless statement? I mean I guess רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir has
to admit eventually that if there's something that just has no value,
it can't mean anything. Right, I don't know for sure what he
would say. Give all you could afford, you know what I mean?
Because the sky, everyone can't live, no one can live without a
sky. Right, yeah, I mean there's a reductio ad absurdum on every
שיטה shita and yeah, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir's cannot obviously be taken
to that extreme. There has to be potentially some logical boundary. Or
לוקה for רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir then? Like do you get, meaning
do you get off or do you get מלקות malkot for saying
something that you can't do? I mean it's not a שבועה shvua
so you're not going to be לוקה for שבועת שוא. shvuat shav.
I mean I think I take a נדר neder. to give the
value of the sky. Right, I mean I think at some point
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir's would have to admit that it's meaningless, but
he will go as far as he can to try and give
meaning to it. No, I know, but then in those cases you
get מלקות malkot or you just get off? I don't know of
any case of מלקות for a נדר. neder So okay, וחכמים אומרים
לא אמר כלום, v'Chachamim omrim lo amar klum, it's a meaningless statement.
So okay, now the גמרא Gemara says רבא חלש, Rava chalash, so
רבא Rava was sick, ולגביה באו רבנן, u'legabei ba'u Rabbanan, so אביי
Abaye and a group of רבנן Rabbanan. went to ביקור חולים, bikur
cholim, they went to visit רבא Rava when he was sick. ויתבי
וקאמרי, v'yasvei v'ka'amri, it's always interesting to see what they talk about
when they're sick. So they're talking about this ברייתא. Baraitah So they
were sitting in front of רבא Rava when he was sick and
they said, they asked רבא, Rava, בשלמא רבי מאיר, bishlama Rabbi Meir,
so I understand רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir, שיטה shita in this ברייתא,
Baraitah קסבר אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה, kasavar ein adam motzi devarav
l'vatala, לא שנא כולו ולא שנא חציו. lo shna kulo v'lo shna
chetzyo.
So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who holds people don't normally make meaningless
statements, so this is completely consistent with what we know
as רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir שיטה. shita.
We already know that he said if you pledge the ערך of
an entire כלי, kli then you have to pay its value. So
likewise here, if you pledge the ערך of half
a כלי, kli then you have to
pay half the value of a כלי.
kli, Then you have to pay half the value of the כלי.
kli אלא רבנן מאי קסברי? ela Rabbanan mai kasavri? So what's the
position of the רבנן?
Rabbanan You mean the same as before?
Oh, except now we're going to be מדייק medayek on the fact
that it said half the value of a כלי, kli. meaning the
half has to be relevant according to someone. So if it's לאו
דווקא lav davka for רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir. we know רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir holds the same
דין din whether you said half the value or the whole value,
then it must be
relevant for
the רבנן. Rabbanan.
It must be that the רבנן Rabbanan hold it's only half the
כלי kli, that's a meaningless statement, but if you
said the ערך of the whole כלי kli you would have to
pay. No, I thought
before that you don't have to pay. Well, different
רבנן. Rabbanan Yes, there exists a שיטה shita that you don't have
to pay. We did discuss that earlier. The גמרא Gemara is assuming
the רבנן Rabbanan. of this ברייתא Baraitah, are different than the רבנן
Rabbanan. of that ברייתא Baraitah because otherwise why would we have to
specify half? But they both say in both cases לא אמר כלום.
lo amar klum.
They do say in both cases לא אמר כלום,
lo amar klum, but they're two different cases and therefore the גמרא
Gemara is assuming they're two different רבנן.
Rabbanan I don't see why you'd say that.
I mean because רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is coming, it's not as
much of the רבנן. Rabbanan Because the רבנן Rabbanan could have just
said it once and you know be done with it, but they're
coming to dispute רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir? Because the רבנן rabanan need,
because you don't need to formulate
a separate ברייתא braita to tell me about half if everyone's שיטה
shita is exactly the same as by the whole thing. The fact
that this is, the גמרא Gemara always does this, every time you
have to formulate a new ברייתא, Brayta. especially you know with a
different word, you have to pick
up on the difference of language and see what does that difference
of language come to teach us. Sometimes a rose is just
a rose.
Not in גמרא. Gemara Except if it's repeated. Right. רבנן מאי קסברי?
Rabbanan mai kasavri? So אי אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה אפילו כולו נמי.
ei adam motzi devarav l'vatala afilu kulo nami. So if people do
make meaningless statements like if they hold like the רבנן rabanan? of
the previous ברייתא Braisa that we saw, then why do you need
to tell me half the
value of the כלי, kli. even the whole value of the כלי
kli you have to pay. ואי אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה אפילו
חציו
נמי.
v'ei ein adam motzi devarav
l'vatala afilu chetzyo nami.
If people don't make meaningless statements, then they should agree with רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir that even half the value you have to pay.
So אמר להו amar lehu
אביי ורבא Abaye v'Rava or רבא ואביי. Rava v'Abaye. So רבא Rava
and אביי Abaye
both came up with
the following answer. רבנן דהכא, rabanan dehacha, the רבנן rabanan in this
ברייתא Braisa כרבי מאיר סברי ליה, keRabbi Meir savri lei, סברי לה,
savri lah, וסברי לה כרבי שמעון. vesavri lah keRabbi Shimon, So they
hold like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir but on a different מחלוקת they
hold like רבי שמעון keRabbi Shimon which is going to create this
distinction between whole and half. סברי לה כרבי מאיר. savri lah keRabbi
Meir. So where, how do they hold like רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir,
דאמר אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה. de'amar ein adam motzi devarav levatala.
They hold like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, that people don't normally make
meaningless statements. וסברי לה vesavri lah כרבי שמעון, keRabbi Shimon. but they
hold like רבי שמעון keRabbi Shimon דאמר de'amar and this, this is
this מחלוקת we saw in מנחות, Menachot, דאמר שלא התנדב כדרך המתנדבים.
de'amar shelo hitnadev kederech hamitnadvim. So רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon holds that
you only have to pay a נדר neder. if it is a
normal way of making a נדר. neder And where it says כולי
אורחיה למתנדבי, kulei orchei lemitnadvei, it's normal for people to pledge the
whole value of a כלי. kli פלגי לאו אורחיה למתנדבי. palgei lav
orchei lemitnadvei. However, it's not normal for, it's not normal for people
to make pledges by saying half the value of something. And therefore,
and therefore that is not a good נדר neder at all. But
when it comes to the, but when it comes to the whole
כלי, that, that is a normal way people make a נדר. neder
What about the second רבנן? rabanan According to the first רבנן it
would be meaningless just as well. Right, according to the first רבנן
you use the לשון ערכין, lashon erchin, so it's already meaningless. However,
even according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that you can translate ערכין
as נדר neder so as not to make the statement meaningless, if
you hold like רבי שמעון, keRabbi Shimon, that's still if it's a
statement that's normal for people to say. So תוספות Tosafot actually asks,
so when is it not normal for people to pledge half the
value of something? And תוספות Tosafot therefore, I've been sort of flipping
up in how I say this throughout, but תוספות Tosafot wants to
change the גרסא girsa of the entire סוגיא sugya to say the
value of half a כלי as opposed to half the value of
a כלי. The value of half a כלי is virtually nothing because
it's a broken כלי and that's just sort of, it has no
value. If you could reuse it, the other half of it has
some value. Right, it has some minuscule amount of value, but like
you don't pledge the value of garbage to the בית המקדש. Beit
HaMikdash. That, that you can see. Right, that's not a normal way
to make a נדר neder to הקדש. hekdesh. Okay, so now the
גמרא gemara, goes, goes on to the next משנה. mishna, האומר ערכו
של פלוני עלי ומת הנודר וכולי. ha'omer erko shel ploni alai umet
hanoder vechulei. And of course the גמרא gemara is going to be
exclusively on וכולי. vechulei? So what was the וכולי? Let's look, look
back at the משנה mishna for a second. האומר ערכו של פלוני
עלי מת הנודר והנידר יתנו היורשין. ha'omer erko shel ploni alai met
hanoder vehanidar yitnu hayorshin. So if you, if you pledge the ערך
of a person and both the pledger and the pledgee died, the
heirs still have to pay. However, and this is the case the
משנה mishna. is going to be dealing with, in a נדרים case,
דמיו של פלוני עלי, damav shel ploni alai, if you make a
נדר neder, for someone's value, מת הנודר, met hanoder, and the pledger
dies, יתנו היורשים, yitnu hayorshim, the heirs still have to pay. מת
הנידר, met hanidar, but if the person whose value is being pledged
dies, לא יתנו היורשים שאין דמים למתים. lo yitnu hayorshim she'ein damim
lemetim. The heirs don't have to pay because again we can't evaluate
the value of someone who's dead. So the גמרא gemara says מני
הא דעמד בדין. mani ha de'amad bedin. If he dies after the
formal valuation then they. If he dies after his price has been
evaluated then they would have to pay. Yeah, we said that before.
So מני הא דעמד בדין. mani ha de'amad bedin. So what's the
case we're dealing with? Like we said in a previous case in
the משנה, mishna we must be dealing with the case where the
נודר, noder, the person making the נדר has already, the court has
already ruled that he has to pay. Right, we already said that's
the case where the יורשין yorshin still have to pay. So the
גמרא gemara says היינו הך, hainu hach, meaning what is this last
part of the משנה mishna. telling us? We already knew that if
you said דמי עלי, demai alai if you've already been evaluated as
having to pay, then you have to pay. So what's the difference
between דמי עלי dmei alai and דמי פלוני עלי? dmei ploni alai?
What's the difference between pledging your own value and pledging someone else's
value? ההלכה hahalachah should, we should just be able to infer the
ההלכה hahalachah is the same thing. So the גמרא gemara says סיפא
איצטריכא ליה. seifa itztreicha lei. No, I do need to know the
end of the משנה. mishna, Why? דמיו של פלוני עלי, damav shel
ploni alai, that should be עלי alai not עליו. alav. דמיו של
פלוני עלי, damav shel ploni alai, if you pledge the value of
another person, ומת הנודר, umet hanoder, יתנו היורשים, yitnu hayorshim, and the
pledger dies. So since, so in the case of, remember in the
case where you're pledging your own value, so we do, the court
does the two things at once, the evaluation that you are indeed
obligated to pay and the evaluation of how much you have to
pay. However, when you're pledging the value of someone else, there are
two different things the court has to do. And we're dealing with
the case now where he dies after the court has evaluated that
he's obligated to pay, but before the court has evaluated the value
of the person who whose value was pledged and therefore we don't
know how much he has to pay. Right, because I mean because
normally we don't, we assume, we assume heirs are always contesting it
because the heirs don't want to have to pay if they don't
have to. So what happens to מצוה לקיים דברי המת? Mitzva lekayem
divrei hamet? Mitzva? But really, you know, real world here. You should,
but we don't force you. Also, we should take care of orphans.
So I might have thought that since, since we don't, since we
don't know the exact value he'll have to pay yet at the
time of death, so there's no, there's no שעבוד נכסים, shibud nekhasim,
there's no lien on the property, and the יורשין, yorshin, the heirs,
only have to pay when there's a lien on the property. קא
משמע לן, Ka mashma lan, so what does the סיפא seifa of
the משנה mishna come to teach us? דכיון דעמד בדין אשתעבדו נכסי.
dekeivan de'amad badin ishtabdu nikhsei. So once, once the court has evaluated
that you have to pay, even if they don't know how much
yet, that already puts a lien on the property. ואומדנא גלויי מילתא
בעלמא היא, ve'umdna giluy milta be'alma hi, and the evaluation of the
value just reveals how much of a lien it is retroactively, but
the lien itself is already there. Okay, we move on to the
next משנה. mishna I'm sorry, wait, so in the case of you
said דמי עלי and then you died, or דמי פלוני עלי dmei
ploni alai and then... Oh right, so in both, that's only if
the pledgee is still alive though, right? Right, if the pledgee is
still alive, you can evaluate his, you can evaluate his value and
then, and then the heirs would have to pay. Moving on to
the next משנה, mishnah so the next משנה mishnah we're moving away
from ערכין altogether and now we're going to be comparing נדרים and
נדבות. nedavot. Different, different types of ways to donate animals to the
בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, either for money or for a קרבן. korban.
So the משנה mishnah, says שור זה עולה, shor zeh olah, this
ox should be a קרבן עולה. korban olah. בית זה קרבן, bayit
zeh korban, this house should be קרבן korban as we see throughout
מסכת נדרים Masechet Nedarim is a way of making something הקדש hekdesh
not just even if it's not an animal that could actually be
brought as a קרבן. korban. Right, right. So if it's, if you
say קרבן korban for something that could be brought as a קרבן,
korban, then it's קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, then that animal itself has
to be brought as a קרבן. korban. If you say it about
something that can't be brought as a קרבן, korban, then then it's
קדושת בדק הבית, kedushat bedek habayit, it goes to the temple treasury.
And so בית זה קרבן, bayit zeh korban, you would have to,
you would have to sell the house and the money goes to
הקדש. hekdesh. Or you could just give the house. I mean, הקדש
hekdesh owns it now. Well, הקדש hekdesh will sell it. They don't
want a house. I don't know, maybe they need storage, maybe they
need to house the כהנים kohanim or whatever it is, you know.
Boom. If it's in ירושלים Yerushalayim maybe. But whatever, yes, they can
do whatever they want with it. So in that case, where you
said this ox should be an עולה olah or this house should
be הקדש, hekdesh, מת השור ונפל הבית, met hashor venafal habayit, so
the ox died or the house fell down, פטור מלשלם. patur milishalem.
So in that case, you're exempt from paying because you didn't take
any... this is going to be the distinction... הרי עלי harei alai
versus הרי זו. harei zu. Right, so what do we need this
here? We've had that like ten times in ש"ס, Shas, haven't we?
Yeah, I mean, I don't know, we're reviewing מסכת נדרים. Masechet Nedarim.
I find it kind of interesting, like sometimes they're like, oh wait,
what does it come to teach us we don't know, and then
they infer some great thing, and other times they have something like
this that's entirely repetitive. Right, I don't know, it's assuming we don't
remember מסכת נדרים Masechet Nedarim I guess, but we don't know the
history that existed, they were talking about reality, even though maybe twenty
years that they had some concept of what it was living in
the temple at the time. Right, so yes, so we are making
the distinction between נדרים and נדבות, nedavot, between זה zeh and עלי,
which in... Right, yes, in classical בריסקער Brisker form, נדרים are a
דין בחפצא, din b'cheftza, the object status changes but you have no,
you haven't taken any personal obligation on yourself, as opposed to נדבה
nedava which is a דין בגברא, din b'gavra, it's not so much
you change the status of the object as you have a personal
obligation to pay, and if you have a personal obligation to pay,
you retain that obligation regardless of what happens to the object. A
נדר is a pledge where you say a specific object is going
to become הקדש hekdesh and a נדבה nedavah is a pledge where
you obligate yourself in a certain value. So alright, so the משנה
mishnah says שור זה עולה shor zeh olah by a קרבן, korban,
מת השור נפלה הבית פטור מלשלם, met hashor naflah habayit patur milishalem,
so if the ox died or if the house fell down you
don't have to pay. However the משנה mishnah contrasts that with שור
זה עלי עולה, shor zeh alai olah, this ox should be on
me as an עולה olah ובית זה עלי קרבן, uvayit zeh alai
korban, if it should be on me in that case מת השור
נפלה הבית חייב לשלם, met hashor naflah habayit chayav lishalem, if the
ox died or if the house fell down you still have to
pay. So in the גמרא, Gemara אמר רבי חייא בר רב, amar
Rabbi Chiya bar Rav, so Rabbi Chiya bar Rav says לא שנו
אלא דאמר דמי שור זה עלי עולה. lo shanu ela de'amar dmei
shor zeh alai olah. So that which the משנה, mishnah, when the
משנה mishnah, said this ox should be on me and עולה olah
and it says that in that case you are still obligated to
pay if the ox dies, that's only if, don't read the משנה
mishnah too literally, that's only if you said דמי שור זה, dmei
shor zeh, if you said the value of this שור. shor. אבל
אמר שור זה עלי עולה, aval amar shor zeh alai olah, but
if you said this, if you didn't say the value of this
ox but you just said this ox should be on me, כיון
דאמר זה ומת אינו חייב באחריותו, keivan de'amar zeh umet eino chayav
beachrayuto, since you said this ox, we assume that you only meant
it as a נדר, you only meant this ox and nothing else
and therefore אינו חייב באחריותו, eino chayav beachrayuto, you don't have to
pay its value if it dies. Okay so what does עלי mean,
why don't we assume that עלי means you were obligating yourself in
the value? עלי להביאו, alai lehavio, you meant it shall be on
me to bring this animal to the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash but
not a proof of the animal. Right. עלי להביאו קאמר, alai lehavio
ka'amar, it is on me to bring it but not it is
on me to pay that value if it dies. So מיתיבי, meitivei,
the גמרא Gemara challenges this from a תוספתא, tosefta, שור זה עולה,
shor zeh olah, so if you say this ox is an עולה,
olah, השור הקדש ומועלין בו, hashor hekdesh umoalin bo, so the ox
itself becomes הקדש, hekdesh, becomes קדושת הגוף, kedushat haguf, and therefore you
could be, you could violate מעילה, meilah, if you get some kind
of benefit from an animal which is הקדש, hekdesh, then you violate
מעילה, meilah, you have to bring your קרבן אשם korban asham for
that. מת או נגנב אינו חייב באחריותו, met o nignav eino chayav
beachrayuto, however if it dies or if it's stolen then you don't
have to pay its value because all you pledged was this ox
and not the value of an ox. Any benefit from that ox?
No because the ox itself is הקדש hekdesh now so it
belongs to the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. But you're still obligated to
give the
skin and the meat or whatever. Right but you don't have to
give the full value of a live ox. Yeah. Contrasting this with
שור זה עלי עולה, shor zeh alai olah, which is exactly the
language of our משנה, mishnah this ox should be on me as
an עולה, olah, השור הקדש, hashor hekdesh,
the animal itself is הקדש, hekdesh, you have, if it's alive you
have to bring that as a קרבן korban ומועלין בו, umoalin bo,
and if you get benefit from it you violate מעילה, meilah, מת
או נגנב חייב באחריותו, met o nignav chayav beachrayuto, however in that
case since you said עלי, if it dies then you have to
pay back its full value. So the גמרא Gemara says can you,
you could use the difference. No it's still הקדש hekdesh and מועלין
בו, moalin bo, it just means that if you do use it
you get, right, anytime that he's saying that formulation gives you the
worst of both worlds, you said זה which makes the animal itself
הקדש hekdesh and you said עלי which obligates you to pay its
full value if it dies. If you pay its full value you
pay the difference? Presumably the difference but that value of it when
it was alive you owe to the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So
the גמרא Gemara says מי אלים ממתניתין, mi alim mimatnitin, like why
yes you brought a תוספתא tosefta with the exact same language as
the משנה, mishnah, דאוקימנא דקאמר דמי, de'okimna deka'amar dmei, and we were
able to make the אוקימתא, okimta, we were able to reinterpret the
משנה Mishnah as when you said the value of, הכא נמי דקאמר
דמי, hacha nami deka'amar dmei, so the same אוקימתא okimta that we
made on the משנה we'll make on the תוספתא. tosefta. The תוספתא
tosefta also when it says
שור זה עלי, shor zeh alai, it's talking about when you said
דמי שור זה עלי, dmei shor zeh
alai, when you said the value of this ox should be on
me. But the גמרא Gemara says
no it's not as easy to make that אוקימתא okimta on the
תוספתא tosefta as on the משנה, והא מדסיפא דקאמר דמי רישא דלא
קאמר דמי, veha mide'seifa deka'amar dmei reisha delo ka'amar dmei, because this
תוספתא tosefta goes on and brings us a case where it explicitly
talks about someone who said the value of the ox and therefore
if the end of the תוספתא tosefta says the value of the
ox it's hard to reinterpret the The beginning of the תוספתא *Tosefta*
is also referring to when you said the value
of the ox because then what's the difference between the רישא *reisha*
and the סיפא *seifa*?
דתני סיפא *D'tani seifa*, so what did the סיפא *seifa* of the
תוספתא *Tosefta* say? דמי שור עולה *D'mei shor olah*, you say the
value of an ox should be an עולה *olah*.
השור חולין *Hashor chullin*, so whatever ox you specifically pointed to is
חולין *chullin*, you don't have to bring that ox at all. ואין
מועלין בו *V'ein mo'alin bo*, and there's no איסור *issur* of מעילה
me'ilah. *me'ilah* if you get benefit from it. מת או נגנב *Meit
o nignav*, if it dies or if it's stolen, אינו
חייב באחריותו אבל חייב באחריות דמיו *eino chayav b'achrayuto aval chayav b'achrayut
damav*. You are not liable for this specific ox because you really
just said the value of an ox, but you are liable for
the value of an ox. אבל חייב באחריות דמיו *Aval chayav b'achrayut
damav*. You don't mean אחריותו *achrayuto*, you don't have to bring another
ox, but you do have to pay its value. And you established
the value of how much it would have produced or how much
it would have been worth when it was alive at that time
of death or generally? Presumably at the time you made the נדר
*neder*. At the time of the הקדש hekdesh. *hekdesh*. Right. Right. So
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say no, רישא וסיפא דקאמר
דמי *reisha v'seifa d'ka-amar d'mei*. No, we're going to make the אוקימתא
*okimta* both the beginning and the end
of the תוספתא
*Tosefta* are referring to a case where you said its value. Okay,
so what's the distinction between the two cases?
We're going to now make much bigger אוקימתות *okimtas* on both of
them
in order for there to be
a realistic distinction. רישא דאמר יקדיש השור לדמיו *Reisha d'amar yakdish
hashor l'damav*.
The רישא *reisha* is where you said this ox should be הקדש
hekdesh.
*hekdesh* for its money. And right, רש"י *Rashi* says הלכך חייב באחריותו
שהרי חל
קדושת דמים על השור והוא קיבל אחריות דמיו *hilkach
chayav b'achrayuto sheharei chal kedushat damim al hashor v'hu kibel achrayut damav*.
So you designated by saying יקדיש השור *yakdish hashor* you designated the
שור *shor* itself as being הקדש hekdesh *hekdesh* and by saying לדמיו
*l'damav* you obligated yourself to pay its value. וסיפא דקאמר לכשיבואו דמיו
יקדשו *V'seifa d'ka-amar l'chsheyavo damav yikdashu*. When its value arrives, meaning the
way רש"י *Rashi* explains that, what you're saying is when I sell
this ox, it will be הקדש hekdesh. *hekdesh*. When I sell this
ox, that money that I get for it will automatically be הקדש
hekdesh. *hekdesh*. And therefore when we said אינו חייב באחריותו אבל חייב
באחריות דמיו *eino chayav b'achrayuto aval chayav b'achrayut damav*, meaning אינו חייב
באחריותו *eino chayav b'achrayuto* with our reinterpretation now meaning if the animal
is no longer intact because or you don't have access to the
animal anymore, then if it dies or it's stolen you don't have
to pay the value of a whole animal. אבל חייב באחריות דמיו
*Aval chayav b'achrayut damav*, but anytime you sell it, including if you
sell the dead carcass, whatever you get for its sale, that money
still has to go to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *Beit HaMikdash*.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* asks about this אוקימתא *okimta*, והא אין
אדם מקדיש דבר שלא בא לעולם Ve-ha ein adam makdish davar she-lo
ba la-olam. *v'ha ein adam makdish davar shelo ba l'olam*. So how
can you say I am מקדיש makdish *makdish*, I'm making, I'm pledging
whatever value I get when I sell this cow or this ox?
I haven't sold the ox yet. That money that I'm going to
get for it doesn't exist yet. And we have a rule that
you can't be מקדיש makdish *makdish* something that does not exist yet.
אמר רב יהודה Rav Yehuda אמר רב Rav, *Amar Rav Yehuda Amar
Rav*, so רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda* says in the name of רב
*Rav*, הא מני *ha manni*? So who's the author of this ברייתא
*braita*? רבי מאיר היא *Rabbi Meir hi*. This ברייתא *braita* is actually
רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. דאמר אדם מקדיש דבר שלא בא לעולם De-amar
adam makdish davar she-lo ba la-olam, *D'amar adam makdish davar shelo ba
l'olam*. רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* in fact holds that you can be
מקדיש makdish *makdish* something which does not exist yet. איכא דאמרי Ika
de-amrei, *Ika d'amri*, there's another version of how this was said, although
it's going to come to the same conclusion. אמר ליה רב פפא
לאביי Amar lei Rav Pappa le-Abaye. *Amar lei Rav Papa l'Abaye*, so
רב פפא *Rav Papa* said to אביי Abaye. *Abaye*, ואמרי לה רמי
בר חמא לרב חסדא Ve-amrei lah Rami bar Chama le-Rav Chisda. *v'amri
lei Rami bar Chama l'Rav Chisda*, and some say that it was
actually רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama *Rami bar Chama* saying to
רב חסדא Rav Chisda. *Rav Chisda*. Sound like a direct quote? Yeah.
כמאן *K'man*? כרבי מאיר *K'Rabbi Meir*. So he said based on the
way you just interpreted our ברייתא *braita*, who is this ברייתא *braita*
according to? רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir*. You know, challenging it as opposed
to... Of course, who else would it be like? Okay, I think
we have time to go on a little further. Okay, so ואיכא
דמתני לה אהא. So there are some who give this entire exchange
about Rabbi Meir and אדם מקדיש דבר שלא בא לעולם Adam makdish
davar she'lo ba l'olam on an entirely different ברייתא. המשכיר בית לחבירו
ונתנגע. Hamaskir bayit l'chaveiro v'nitnaga. So if a person rents out a
house to his friend, to another person, and then it got נגעים,
nega'im, the house got צרעת. tzara'at. So if a house gets... how
do you have that clause in the contract? Right. So if a
house gets צרעת, tzara'at, first it gets condemned by the כהן kohen
and then it has to be destroyed. So אף על פי שחלטו
כהן, af al pi she'chalto kohen, even though the כהן kohen has
condemned it, אומר הרי שלך לפניך. omer harei shelcha lefanecha. So the
owner, the landlord can say to the renter, "You leased the house,
here's a house. Alright, it's going to be destroyed, but you know,
and it's probably אסור בהנאה assur b'hana'ah from the time it's condemned
until the time it's destroyed." But presumably it's only if you lease
this house, right? Like let's say I lease a house from you
and then you give me the one with צרעת, tzara'at, you can't
do that, can you? It seems it has to... if it develops
צרעת tzara'at after you sign the contract is what we're talking about.
No, no, but let's say I sign a contract for a house.
Can you then just decide to give me the one with צרעת?
tzara'at? No, probably not. For this house. I rented a specific house
from you and then it got צרעת tzara'at and says here's the
house I rented to you, even
though it's going to be
worthless to you pretty soon. נתצו חייב להעמיד לו בית. Nitzo chayav
l'ha'amid lo bayit. However, once it's actually destroyed, then I have to
give you another house to live in. הקדישו הדר בו. Hikdisho hadar
bo. If the one who is
living in it is מקדיש makdish it, מעלה שכר להקדש, ma'aleh sechar
l'hekdesh, then the rent that he pays goes to הקדש. hekdesh But
he has to pay the rent
to the owner and also the rent to the הקדש. hekdesh Meaning
because if it's your house... so the גמרא Gemara. is going to
ask, הקדישו הדר בו היכי מצי? Hikdisho hadar bo heichi matzi? היכי
מצי מקדיש לה? Heichi matzi makdish la? How could the person who's
living in it, who is the renter, be מקדיש makdish it? איש
כי יקדיש ביתו קדש אמר רחמנא. Ish ki yakdish beito kodesh amar
rachmana. מה ביתו ברשותו אף כל ברשותו. Ma beito birshuto af kol
birshuto. So in the פסוק about הקדש hekdesh it says, "A person
who is מקדיש makdish his house," and the דרשה drasha on that
פסוק is, just like your house is in your possession, so too
you can only
be מקדיש makdish something that's
in your possession. So you can't be מקדיש makdish something that's not
yours. What does it mean that the person who is living there
was מקדיש makdish, it? הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. So this is how
you should read it. And the גמרא is going to basically just
punctuate it differently. It's הקדישו, hikdisho, meaning הקדישו משכיר, hikdisho maskir, the
landlord, the landlord is מקדיש makdish it. הדר בו מעלה שכר להקדש.
Hadar bo ma'aleh sechar l'hekdesh. If the landlord is מקדיש makdish it,
the one who is living there now pays the rent to הקדש.
hekdesh? But that's מעילה. me'ilah. So meaning... that's probably after he already
rented it, then he said, "Oh, you know, then I want to
be מקדיש," Makdish presumably. That's the גמרא's next question. Okay. But is
this a separate case from צרעת tzara'at or are they connecting it?
This is an entirely separate case from צרעת, tzara'at, yeah. This is
just what happens if you... two separate cases where I rent you
a house and then something about the house changes. So in the
first case the house got צרעת, tzara'at, in this case
I was מקדיש Makdish the house. Contract law. Right. So the גמרא
asks, הקדישו משכיר היכי דייר ביה? Hikdisho maskir heichi dayer bei? How
can he continue to live in it if the landlord has been
מקדיש Makdish it? במעילה קאי. B'me'ilah ka'i. He'd be violating מעילה.
me'ilah. You can't get any sort of benefit from הקדש. Hekdesh, But
if הקדש Hekdesh. are getting... but if they're getting the proceeds, they're
getting the rent maybe. No, הקדש Hekdesh, cannot rent things out because
as long as they own the object, no one's allowed to get
any benefit from it.
But even they're not allowed to get the benefit of the money?
Yeah, they could sell it, but... eventually to the כהן? kohen? No,
I don't know. It's... no, I mean maybe they
could let a כהן kohen live in it for free, I don't
know, but not... if that's the needs of the בית המקדש. But
yeah, normally an object which belongs to הקדש Hekdesh? cannot be rented
out because no one can get benefit from the object.
The only thing they can do with it is sell it. So
first of all, how can he live there? He'd be violating מעילה.
Me'ilah And two, מעלה שכר להקדש, ma'aleh sechar l'hekdesh, even if he
is living there for whatever reason, why would he have to pay
the money to הקדש? Hekdesh, כיון דמעל ביה נפיק ליה שכר לחולין.
Keivan d'maal
bei nafik lei sechar l'chullin.
Once... Once we have a rule אין מעילה אחר מעילה. Ein Me'ilah
achar Me'ilah. Once you, once you do מעילה Me'ilah, once, once you
get benefit inappropriately from הקדש, Hekdesh.
so that object is no longer הקדש. Hekdesh. You have, you've violated
the איסור מעילה, Issur Me'ilah, but you've successfully removed the קדושה Kedushah
from that object. So once you're living in there and violating מעילה,
so the house is no longer הקדש, Hekdesh, so the rent on
it should be חולין as well. Why would you have to, why
would you have to give the rent to
הקדש? Hekdesh? So, so, so the גמרא says
now it's a different case we're dealing with. We're not dealing with
the case where the landlord was מקדיש Makdish the actual house. We're
dealing with the case where the landlord said דאמר לכשיבוא שכר יקדש.
De-amar lich-she-yavo sachar yikdash. So basically the person says, the person says
the house isn't הקדש, Hekdesh, but whenever the rent arises, the rent
payment should automatically be הקדש. Oh, so that's his point. In other
words, right, profits of the apartment go to הקדש. Right. So then
the גמרא asks, and now this is what ties it back to
where we started, because the גמרא asks the same question they asked
originally on
our גמרא. והא אין אדם
מקדיש Makdish דבר שלא בא לעולם. But how can you, this rent
payment hasn't been paid yet, it doesn't exist yet, how can you
be מקדיש Makdish something which doesn't exist yet? אמר אמר רב יהודה
אמר רב. Amar amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav. So רב יהודה says
in the name of רב, הא מני רבי מאיר היא. Ha mani
Rabbi Meir hi. This ברייתא is actually רבי מאיר, דאמר אדם מקדיש
דבר שלא בא לעולם, De-amar adam makdish davar she-lo ba la-olam, who
holds you can be מקדיש something that doesn't exist yet. And איכא
דאמרי, the other version that we had before, אמר ליה רב פפא
לאביי. רב פפא said to אביי. ואמרי לה רמי בר חמא לרב
חסדא. And some say it was רמי בר חמא to רב חסדא.
כמאן כרבי מאיר? Ke-man ke-Rabbi Meir? Are you assuming that this ברייתא
is like רבי מאיר, דאמר אדם מקדיש דבר שלא בא לעולם, who
holds that a person can be מקדיש something that doesn't exist in
the world yet? אמר ליה באלא כמאן? Amar lei be-ela ke-man? Yeah,
of course, who else would it be like? And we will stop
here. Did you say in the last case that the house was
not הקדש, just the rent was made הקדש? Right, the last case
is when the rent was made הקדש, and then we're dealing with
how can you be מקדיש rent that hasn't been paid yet, and
we say oh, it must be like רבי מאיר who holds you
can be מקדיש something that doesn't exist yet. Was there, I don't
know if we studied it here or I read it somewhere else,
wasn't there רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said that people don't make meaningless
statements? I don't know. Have you come across that? No idea. Maybe
I read it in a משנה commentary that because he was always
so involved with people that... Oh, we did see a couple of
days ago, yeah, not about
a whole statement being meaningless, but about assuming that people don't add
extra words to their statements meaninglessly.
Yeah, we did see that. יישר כח. Yasher koach.